Guide to the Microtonal Music Archive, 1943-2010 MUS.2019.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Microtonal Music Archive
1943-2010
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Rosenblum, Mathew
MUS.2019.01
3 boxes
This archive, a major resource for research and performance, brings together materials in various formats (scores, recordings, correspondence) that cover the expanse of microtonal music in the United States, and features works by Mathew Rosenblum, Dean Drummond, and Ezra Sims, among others. Some commercially released scores and recordings from the archive are housed in the collections of the Theodore M. Finney Music Library.
Scope and Content Notes
The collection contains manuscripts and computer-generated scores of works of microtonal music by several composers. It is divided into two series: Series I: Composers; Series II: Organizations. Unless otherwise noted, there is one copy of each item listed.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acqusition Information
Major portions of this collection were a gift of Mathew Rosenblum on August 26, 2019.
Accruals
New material is expected to be donated on an ongoing basis.
Rosenblum, Mathew
- Composers, 1943-2010; I.
  - Ezra Sims, 1980-1997; 1.
    - Works, 1980-1989
      - Brief Elegies, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Scope and Contents
        Extent: 7 pages; 34 cm, Scoring: Flute, zoomoozophone, clarinet in A, bassoon, trombone, double bass, Notes: Autograph manuscript. At end: Cambridge / 24 August '83. Ratios for notes entered into score by Dean Drummond in pencil. Tunings given on p. 7. Other markings in red pencil.
      - Brief Elegies, revised 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Notes: Performing parts used by Newband for DX7II (7 pages; pp. 6-7 provide tunings), markings in black and red pencil, at end: rev. / 13 Jan 89. / Cambridge; flute (2 pages), tuning ratios given in black pencil above notes; zoomoozophone (2 copies; copy 1 has written on caption in red ink: Greg I), 5 pages each, markings in black and red pencil.
      - Two for One, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Extent: [8] pages; 36 cm (spiral bound), Scoring: Violin, viola, Notes: Two copies. Both copies have markings in black pencil. At end (copy 1): Cambridge 1980. Keys of Two for one pasted on inside cover of copy 2.
    - Correspondence, 1986-1997
      - Correspondence with Mathew Rosenblum, 1986-1997 (Box 1, Folder 3a)
  - Mathew Rosenblum, c. 2008-2011; 2.
    - Harp Quartet, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Extent: 34 pages; 28 x 42 cm, Scoring: Alto flute (doubling on flute), bass clarinet (doubling on clarinet in Bb), viola, harp, Notes: Ozalid score (spiral bound). On overleaf: In Memory of My Father. On caption: for Susan Allen. Abbreviations and instrumental symbols precede score. Contents: Morning dialogue – Shimmering and transparent.
    - Yonah's Dream, 2008; revised 2011 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Extent: 12 parts (various pagings); 28 cm, Scoring: Flute, crychord, surrogate kithara, diamond marimba, bamboo marimba, bass marimba, and spoils of war, Notes: Some parts are spiral bound, others loose pages. Markings in black pencil in some of the parts.
    - Ancient Eyes (Egyptian Lullaby), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Extent: 4 parts; 43 cm, Scoring: Flute, clarinet in Bb, keyboards 1-2, Notes: Spiral bound. At head of title: for Anna Eileen. Performing parts used by Newband. Markings in black pencil in each part. Clarinet and cello parts are highlighted in yellow (clarinet) and green (cello).
    - Continental Drift, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Extent: 18 pages; 43 cm, Scoring: Clarinet in Bb, percussion, zoomoozophone, harp, and DX7, Notes: Clarinet part used in performance by Newband. Markings in black and red pencil predominately in the clarinet part.
    - Conductor score, undated (Box 1, Folder 7a)
      Extent: 22 leaves; 47 cm, Notes: Individual pages of the full score taped onto cardboard backing. Markings in black pencil. Used by Newband in performance?
  - Harry Partch, 1943-2000; 3.
    - Dark Brother, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Extent: 17 pages; 36 cm, Scoring: Voice, adapted viola, chromolodeon, kithara, bass marimba, Notes: Annotated by Dean Drummond. Spiral bound. On caption: To Allen H. Klinger. "Final two paragraphs from Thomas Wolfe's 'God's Lonely Man'" under title. Markings in black and red pencil throughout. On cover in red pencil: JUDY. At end: Chappaqua-Ithaca-Sept. 1992 to June 21, 1.
    - Eleven Intrusions, 1946-1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Extent: [22] pages; 28 cm, Scoring: Various, including harmonic canon, guitar, voice, bass marimba, diamond marimba, and chorus, Notes: Spiral bound. On overleaf: Two studies on ancient Greek scales. Markings in black and red ink throughout. On cover in red pencil: JUDY. Contents: Study on Olympos' pentatonic – Study on Arechytas' enharmonic (at end: Madison, 1946, spring / Bass marimba part added, / Gualala, 1950) – The rose (Ella Young) (at end: Gualala, summer, 1949) – The crane (Tsuryuki-Waley) (at end: Gualala, summer, 1950) – The waterfall (Ella Young) (at end: Gualala, summer, 1949) – The wind (Ella Young – Lao-tze) (at end: Gualala, March, 1950) – The street (Willard Motley) (at end: Gualala, March, 1950) – Lover (George Leite) (at end: Gualala, Sept., 1950) – Soldiers – War – Another war (Ungaretti) (at end: Gualala, November, 1950) – Vanity (Ungaretti) (at end: Gualala, December 19, 1950) – Cloud-chamber music ((Ungaretti) (at end: Gualala, December 30, 1950).
    - U.S. Highball, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Extent: 47 pages; 41 cm, Scoring: Voices (baritone, bass), kithara II, surrogate kithara, Castor, Pollux (played by one person), chromolodeon, diamond marimba (and spoils of war), bass marimba, boo (bamboo marimba), Notes: Spiral bound. Subtitle: A musical account of a transcontinental hobo trip. History of work given in foreword on titlepage. At end: Rewritten at Gate 5 – June 30, 1955. Markings in black and red pencil, and blue ink.
    - And on the Seventh Day Petals Fell in Petaluma, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Extent: 39 pages; 28 cm, Scoring: Adapted guitar, Castor & Pollux, blue rainbow, koto, spoils of war, cloud-chamber bowls, boo (bamboo marimba), kithara I (alto kithara), kithara II (bass kithara), surrogate kithara, diamond marimba, marimba eroica, bass marimba, bloboy, chromolodeon I, chromolodeon II, gourd tree, cone gongs, zymo-xyl, xyl, Notes: In cloth binder. Tunings precede score. On titlepage: Twenty-three one-minute duets and trios which later became ten quartets and quintets and one septet. / Studies in techniques, timbres, double rhythms, double tonalities. / Originally written in Petaluma 1963-4 and revised in Del Mar, Van Nuys, Venice, in the years since. / H.P.—1966. Markings in black pencil throughout. At end: This copy made at San Diego, October, 1966.
  - Dean Drummond, 1967-1997; 4.
    - Incredible Time (To Live and Die), 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Extent: 91 pages; 28 cm, Scoring: amplified flute, Yamaha DX7 II, zoomoozophone, percussion, digital drums (3 players), Notes: Spiral bound. Performance notes precede score. At end: 4-5-88 / NYC.
    - Incredible Time (To Live and Die), 1997 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Extent: 91 pages; 28 cm, Scoring: amplified flute, Yamaha DX7 II synthesizer, zoomoozophone, percussion, digital drums (3 players), Notes: Revised version, 1997. Spiral bound. Performance notes precede score. At end: 4-5-88 / NYC.
    - Before the Last Laugh, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Extent: 67 pages; 28 cm, Scoring: flute, cello, Yamaha DX7 II synthesizer, three harmonic canons (two players), zoomoozophone, percussion (two players), Notes: Spiral bound. Performance notes and harmonic canon tunings precede score. Markings in black and red pencil and blue and green ink throughout. On titlepage: This score needs minor corrections. In red pencil on titlepage: Judy, there is some mis-numbering on take sheet…On bottom of last page in black pencil: Judy / I heard noise on every / take. I really want the / flute from take 49 for all / of bar 220 (your bar 219 due / to misnumbering). Can anything / be done about the noise? I'm / willing to consider a slightly / hastened decay. / Thanks, / Dean. At end: 9-4-95 / Purchase, NY.
    - Duo for Soprano Saxophone & Horn, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Extent: 9 pages; 28 cm. Scoring: soprano saxophone in Bb, French horn in F, Notes: Spiral bound. Pages 2 and 3 reversed.
    - The Day the Sun Stood Still, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Extent: 80 pages; 28 cm, Scoring: flute, trumpet, cello, synthesizer Yamaha DX7 II, 2 harmonic canons (one player), four percussionists playing zoomoozophone, juststrokerods, and sex Harry Partch instruments, Notes: Spiral bound. Performance notes and tunings precede score. Commissioned by the Fromm Music Foundation at Harvard University. At end: 8-24-94 / Purchase, NY / 12-94 revision.
    - Ruby Half Moon, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Extent: 92 pages; 28 cm, Scoring: 2 trumpets in C, tenor trombone, bass trombone, zoomoozophone, percussion (4 players), Notes: Spiral bound. Performance notes and tunings precede score. At end: 4-1-87 / NYC.
    - The Last Laugh (and For the Last Laugh), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Extent: 463 pages; 28 cm, Scoring: flute in C, alto flute in G, cello, Yamaha DX 7 II synthesizer, chromolodeon, two harmonic canons, kithara II, bass marimba, rhythm boat, 2 Balinese angklungs, zoomoozophone, bongos, spoils of war, medium Chinese tom tom, steel bowl, Peking Opera gong, two Chinese cymbals, sleigh bells, diamond marimba, boo, bloboy, juststrokerods, hi-hat, Notes: Spiral bound. Based on the film The Last Laugh (Der letzte Mann) by F. W. Murnau. For Bruce Ide & Lois V Vierk. Commission made possible by a grant from the Meet the Composer/Reader's Digest Commissioning Program, in partnership with the National Endowment for the Arts and the Lila Wallace-Reader's Digest Fund. Performance notes, tunings, and notes on the coordination with the film precede the score.
    - Mysteries (Quintet version), 1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Extent: 41 pages; 28 cm, Scoring: 4 zoomoozophones, percussion (1 player), Notes: Incomplete? Ends at m. 205. Markings in black pencil throughout.
    - Ni kioku, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Extent: 39 pages; 28 cm, Scoring: Flute (and rattle), percussion (2 players), harp, celeste, violin, cello. Notes: Spiral bound. Imprint on cover: New York, NY: American Composers Alliance. Markings in black pencil and purple marker (possibly conducting cues).
    - Dance of the Seven Veils, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Extent: A-B, 83 pages; 28 cm, Scoring: Flute in C, cello, chromelodeon, Yamaha DX7 II, zoomoozophones, harmonic canons, various percussion instruments. Notes: Spiral bound. Performance notes precede score. At end: Upper Nyack, NY, 9-30-92, 12-9-92 revision. At bottom of titlepage: For the Serge Koussevitzky Music Foundation in the Library of Congress and dedicated to the memory of Serge & Natalie Koussevitzky.
    - Post Rigabop Mix, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Extent: 5 leaves; 22 x 28 cm (3 copies), Scoring: solo flute. Notes: On cover: To Stefani. May be played alone or with other pieces of set: Bardamu Music.
    - Then or Never, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Extent: 46 pages; 42 cm, Scoring: flute, viola, double bass, 3 zoomoozophones. Notes: Formerly spiral bound. third zoomoozophone part highlighted in yellow. On cover in red pencil: Old Score. Dedicated to Jimmy Pugliese and Dominic Donato.
  - Elizabeth Walsh, 2001-2005; 5.
    - Radium, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Extent: [24] pages; 28 cm (2 copies), Scoring: kithara II, 3 zoomoozophones, diamond marimba, and bass marimba. Notes: Spiral bound. Copy 1 has markings in red pencil and highlighting in yellow. On cover: "Zoomoozophone 2 and bass marimba parts can be performed by the same person". On cover of copy 1: New Score (in black pencil); Capital letter "D" in red pencil, possibly Dean Drummond's conductor score?
    - The Lesson of the Moth, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Extent: 14 pages; 35 cm (copy 1), 41 pages; 43 cm (copy 2), Scoring: Tenor voice, chromelodeon, spoils of war, boo, adapted guitar. Notes: Text by e.e. cummings. Both spiral bound. Copy 1 is basically a vocal/conductor score, while copy 2 is a full score. Copy 1 has markings in black and red pencil. At bottom of first page of copy 1: Sound check, 1:00, 4/6/03. On cover of copy 2: Willie Favors, tenor. Performance notes in copy 2 has different title: The Lesson of the Cockroach, with cockroach scratched out, and moth written in above.
    - Inside the Ice House, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Extent: 34 pages; 28 cm (2 copies), Scoring: violin, surrogate kithara, zoomoozophone, hydronica, bass marimba, spoils of war, and cone gongs. Notes: Spiral bound. Copy 1 has markings in red pencil and highlighting in yellow. On cover of copy 1: Capital letter "D" in red pencil, possibly Dean Drummond's conductor score?
  - David Rosenthal, 1973-1978; 6.
    - Helix Song, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Extent: 3 pages; 28 cm, Scoring: Cheng, metallophone, marimba I, marimba II. Notes: Dedicated to Erv Wilson. Includes parts to the arrangement by Dean Drummond for clarinet in Bb, cello, zoomoozophones 1-3; parts on ozalid, pasted onto hardboard, or written in pencil on transparency.
    - Untitled Work, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Extent: 21 leaves; 22 x 47 cm, Scoring: includes vibraphone, crotales, glockenspiel, and cymbal. Three staves do not identify instrument. Notes: On transparency. At end: May 7, 1973, Val Verde, California.
  - Paul West, 2010; 7.
    - On the Road, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Extent: 7 leaves; 28 cm, Scoring: voice, chromelodeon, and upright bass. Notes: Text by Jack Kerouac. Photocopy. At end: Revised – Los Angeles, Winter-Spring 2010.
  - Gregg Rossetti, 2006; 8.
    - Mutating Aeon, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Extent: 17 pages; 43 cm, Scoring: bass marimba, chromelodeon, diamond marimba, 43-tone harmonic canon, zoomoozophone. Notes: Spiral bound. Markings in orange and black pencil; highlighting in yellow. Possibly used as conductor score by Newband.
  - Manfred Stahnke, 1987-1993; 9.
    - En Cet Hybride Tamps, 1987-1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Extent: 42 pages; 30 cm, Scoring: two violins, 2 violas, four clarinets in Bb, harp, microtone-synthesizer (or sampler), 2 percussionists, and tape (or computer). Notes: Spiral bound. Subtitle on cover: Interlocking zwischen Afrika und Europa. Performance notes precede score.
    - Halakiltunti, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Extent: 50 pages; 30 cm, Scoring: trumpet in C, trumpet in B, tenor trombone, percussion (2 players), 2 violins, and viola. Notes: Spiral bound. Program notes in German precede score. On cover: "von der Hessischen Kulturstiftung in Auftrag gegeben dem 'ensemble modern' gewidmet.
  - Muhal Richard Abrams, c. 1995; 10.
    - New Horizons, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Extent: 133 pages; 28 cm, Scoring: flute, cello, DX7, harmonic canon, zoomoozophones, s. rods, diamond marimba, bowls, spoils of war, and gongs. Notes: Spiral bound. Markings in red and black pencil; highlighting in yellow. Possibly conductor score for Newband.
    - Parts., undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Extent: 11 parts; 28 cm. Notes: Markings in black pencil in several of the parts.
  - Eric Mandat, 1980; 11.
    - Tricolor Capers, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Extent: 8 pages; 32 cm, Scoring: solo clarinet. Notes: Ozalid score. Includes sheet of suggested fingerings for the microtones.
  - Anne LeBaron, 1993; 12.
    - Southern Ephemera, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Extent: 29 pages; 28 cm, Scoring: flute (also alto flute), cello, harmonic canon, and surrogate kithara. Notes: On caption: for Melissa Delbridge. General notes and reference chart for surrogate kithara pitches precede score. At end: Washington, D.C., 1/29/93.
  - Elizabeth Brown, 2008; 13.
    - Seahorse, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Extent: 43 pages; 28 cm, Scoring: theremin, guitar, harmonic canon, chromolodeon, diamond marimba, bass marimba, zoomoozophone, and juststrokerods. Notes: Spiral bound. Notes to performers printed on inside cover. On caption: for Dean Drummond and the Partch Ensemble. Markings in red, blue and black pencil; highlighting in yellow. On cover: large capital "D" in pencil. Possibly conductor score for Newband.
  - Donald Steven, 2001; 14.
    - ô, to make dreames true, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Extent: 10 pages; 28 x 43 cm, Scoring: various, including voices, flute, alto flute, kithara, speaker, surrogate kithara, juststrokerods, cone gongs, cloud chamber bowls, spoils of war, chromelodeon, diamond marimba, and adapted viola. Notes: Markings in black pencil. On cover" Commissioned by Newband with the generous support of the New York State Council on the Arts". Also on cover: "Stockbridge, Massachusetts, June 2, 2001".
  - David J. Simons, 2005-2006; 15.
    - Odentity, 2005; revised 2006 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Extent: 47 pages; 22 x 28 cm, Scoring: guitar, harmonic canon, chromelodeon, zoomoozophones, diamond marimba, boo (bamboo marimba), and bass marimba. Notes: Spiral bound. Microtones designated on titlepage. On cover: "Composed, in part, thanks to a residency at the Rockefeller Foundation Bellagio study center, Lago di Como, Italy". Markings in black and red pencil; highlighting in yellow. On caption: for Newband and the Harry Partch Instruments. Possibly conductor score for performance by Newband.
  - Lasse Thoresen, c. 1990; 16.
    - Thus, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Extent: 118 pages; 43 cm (2 copies), Scoring: flute, clarinet, percussion (3 players), zoomoozophone, Yamaha Dx7 II synthesizer. Notes: Older version of the score. Copy 1 is incomplete. Markings in red and black pencil, whiteout. On cover of copy 1: Dean. Copy 2 has markings in red pencil. On titlepage: "Commissioned for Newband by the Norwegian Section of ISCM ('Foreningen Ny Musikk') for performance during the World Music Days in Oslo September 1990".
    - Parts. Various pagings., undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Organizations (For future materials), II.